<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Palæmon, or, The grand reconciler composing the great difference and disputes about church-government and discovering the primitive government of churches, built upon the Word of God, and the practice of the apostles / compiled by one who labours for the peace of the church.</title>
            <author>T. N.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52993</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N77</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30734</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11466743</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11466743</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47763</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52993)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47763)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1467:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Palæmon, or, The grand reconciler composing the great difference and disputes about church-government and discovering the primitive government of churches, built upon the Word of God, and the practice of the apostles / compiled by one who labours for the peace of the church.</title>
                  <author>T. N.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: T.N.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government.</term>
               <term>Church polity.</term>
               <term>Episcopacy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47763:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47763:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PALAEMON, <hi>OR,</hi> The Grand Reconciler: Compoſing the great Difference and Diſputes about <hi>Church-Government.</hi> AND Diſcovering the Primitive Government of Churches, built upon the Word of God, and the practice of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Compiled by one who labours for the Peace of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <bibl>Can. Conc. Nic.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JEREM. 6.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Aske for the old way, which is the good way.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> MDCXLVI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:47763:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47763:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE To all true-hearted Chriſtians and good Subjects, who deſire a bleſſed Conjuncture of Truth and Peace, and an happy Reformation in the State and Church.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S <hi>Sufferers</hi> may complaine, and <hi>Sorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> ſpeake, ſo we Divines who are <hi>Seers</hi> ought not to be ſilent, when we diſcover a Quick-ſand of errour, or any rocks of ſin, at which a ſoul may daſh to its eternall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. There is a <hi>Coward</hi> in the field, who is like the Wiſe-mans foole, his heart is at his mouth, and he knowes not what he does profeſſe, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting even that he weares a <hi>Sword</hi> for his defence. There is likewiſe a <hi>Coward</hi> in his faith, who is like a foole that ſeemes wiſe, for his mouth is in his heart, and he dares not profeſſe what he knowes, not remembring that God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him the publication of his <hi>Word;</hi> at which the men of this world take offence, and had rather be fed with pleaſing truths to their deſtruction, then heare of true Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which croſſes them in their pride and ambition. I am perſwaded this enſuing Treatiſe will offend thoſe who being of <hi>Aerius</hi> his ſpirit, oppoſe moderated Epiſcopacie, for no other
<pb facs="tcp:47763:3"/>end but that they themſelves might Lord it over Gods heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage with a Tyrannicall Inſolencie. The Character which <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> faſtens upon ſome proud Heretiques in his time,<note place="margin">Hom. 8. in Gen.</note> will fit with ſuch mens arrogant conditions, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. They pretend Piety and Moderation, but if they were throughly ſifted, and their thoughts ript up, we ſhould finde a Lions heart under a Sheeps skinne. That which they doe but pretend, is our totall aime, and that is <hi>Moderation;</hi> a Vertue ſo admired by that Secretarie of a French King, that being commanded by his Soveraigne to ſet downe in writing the beſt word that he ever met with in all his reading, he writ in a ſheet of paper the French word which is ſutable with our Engliſh, <hi>Moderation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is for want of this, that men (as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpeaks) runne headlong into precipices of Schiſmes and Diviſions.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. In Gen.</note> It is for want of this, that to repaire an accident, the ſubſtance is deſtroyed; as when inſtead of paring a mans nailes, one ſhould cut off his head.</p>
            <p>It is for want of this that a Calling found and built upon the Scriptures, allowed of by all Councels, and for <hi>1500.</hi> yeers ſettled without gain-ſaying in all Reformed Churches, ſhould now be cryed downe as illegitimate and ſpurious, and all for the defect of ſome Perſons.</p>
            <p>Let us then have no <hi>Generalls,</hi> becauſe ſome have beene found tardie in the execution of their Commiſsions: Let us have no more <hi>Captaines,</hi> becauſe ſome have been faulty in the diſcharge of their duties: No more Judges, becauſe ſome have perverted the Lawes by their falſe gloſſes.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake this with griefe; Conſidering what a ſhame it will be to our Nation, when it ſhall be reported in After-Ages, that inſtead of taking off the moſſe, and ſcraping off the mould, that adhered to the fabrick of our Churches admired
<pb facs="tcp:47763:3"/>government, the whole building was deſtroyed, and another ſet up greater in bulk, and not conſiſting with Monarchy &amp; the liberty of the Subject, ſuch is a Presbyterie. Which I could prove, and which Idol I would court and labour to ſet up, if I were an <hi>Aerian, i.e.</hi> ambitious, if I deſired <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Ariſtoph. in Nub.</note> to ride upon the neckes of the Gentry, and the ſhoulders of my Pariſhioners; being thus mounted I ſhould be ſhot at with envy and hatred, which would be a meanes to hinder the paſſage of the Goſpel, and choke the ſeed of the Word, which takes root in thoſe hearts only that are garniſhed with love and liking to their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</p>
            <p>Againe, when I conſider with ſorrow and teares the ſad diſtempers, the many Schiſmes and Hereſies under which the Church now labours with ſhame and ſcorne from its enemies, I muſt needs ſubmit to the judgement of a wiſe man, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes of an impoſsibility to ſettle theſe diſorders, to ſuppreſſe the daring boldneſſe of Anabaptiſts and other Schiſmatickes, unleſſe there be ſet over the Presbyters in every Province grave and wiſe <hi>Overſeers, i.e.</hi> Biſhops to reſtraine by their authority grounded upon the Law ſuch mens bold. attempts, who flye even at the Crowne, and ſow the ſeeds of errours in the mindes of poore Chriſtians, who ſwallow all doctrines, if uſhered with a ſeeming authority from the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>And ſoraſmuch as every Sect will be buſie in tempting o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers after it, and ſo make a fatall rupture in the body, and teare the Church in pieces by their multiplied diviſions; no better way is conceived to prevent theſe fearfull, miſchiefes, and to re-eſtabliſh <hi>Unity</hi> both in <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Worſhip,</hi> in the Church, then to inveſt one with power, who not med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with temporall affaires, ſhall (with the advice and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of a few grave Presbyters, aſsiſting him in his monethly Viſitation) ſtrangle Schiſme in the Cradle, nip it in the bud, and ſee that all inferiour Miniſters diſcharge their functions
<pb facs="tcp:47763:4"/>both in <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Life.</hi> The laſt of which (as the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of <hi>Paris</hi> once ſaid) is the beſt Oratour to perſwade,<note place="margin">Gerſon.</note> and the beſt Comment upon the Word, and therefore it is moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that every Miniſter be reformed himſelfe, if he means to inſtruct others in the way to heaven and happineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Epiſcopacy moderated</hi> promiſes this reformation in the Church. It was that whereby <hi>Crathilinth</hi> King of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who ſucceeded <hi>Donald,</hi> ſetled the Goſpel of Chriſt in his Kingdome, with the extirpation of idolatry, which the Druides thoſe idolatrous Prieſts had ſet up in thoſe parts. The godly Miniſters, by whoſe ayd and aſsiſtance the King did this, were termed <hi>Colidei</hi> or <hi>Culdees;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Veteres Scoto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Epiſcopi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Monaſteriis electi cum ad huc non honor is &amp; lucri, ſed ſanctitatis &amp; doctrinae certa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men inter eos eſſet, &amp;c. <hi>Buch. hiſt.</hi>
               </note> who, as <hi>Buchanan</hi> himſelfe aſſerts, choſe out of themſelves eminent men in piety and knowledge, to overſee the reſt, and to keepe them to the performance of their miniſteriall offices, with a diſcreet car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of each one towards another in their ſeverall Societies; thoſe <hi>Overſeers Buchanan</hi> calls <hi>Epiſcopos, Biſhops,</hi> not <hi>Superintendants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, Epiſcopacy thus moderated will be (by Gods bleſsing) a meanes to reduce things and perſons to that purity which God expects of us, and which once acquired the Sword ſhall <hi>turne againe into the ſcabard,</hi> our Wars will ceaſe.</p>
            <p>I know that middle counſels ever diſpleaſed both parties that were at ods and variance:<note place="margin">Hiſt. c. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>437.</hi>
               </note> a proofe hereof we have in Pope <hi>Pius</hi> (rather <hi>Impius</hi>) the <hi>4.</hi> in the Councell (or rather Conventicle) of <hi>Trent;</hi> and I doubt not but by propounding this way of moderation I ſhall purchaſe many enemies, and loſe more friends: However I ſhall comfort my ſelfe with that ſaying of the Apoſtle, <hi>If I ſeeke to pleaſe men I am not the ſervant of Chriſt.</hi> And I ſhall intreat all my fellow-labourers in Geds Vineyard, the Miniſters of the Word and Sacraments,<note place="margin">V. 3, 4, 5.</note> to looke into the <hi>13.</hi> Chapter of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> where a <hi>woe</hi> is pronounced againſt thoſe Prophets, <hi>who are like
<pb facs="tcp:47763:4"/>the Foxes in the Deſerts, i.e.</hi> hide their heads, <hi>which go not up into the gaps, neither make up the hedge of the houſe of Iſrael.</hi> This Text ſet a ſpurre to my backward in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions; it ſtirred me up to ſnatch a Candle out of another mans hand <hi>to give light to them that are in darkneſſe,</hi> and are miſled with corrupt and blinde Teachers; whoſe aime is to pull others out of their ſeats that they may ſtep into them themſelves: and when ſuch giddy-braine <hi>Drivers</hi> ſhall get into the Chariot box, when men led with Phanſie and Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall ſit at the Helme of our Church, then <hi>woe</hi> be to the State, <hi>woe</hi> be to the Kingdome. I feare they will encreaſe our miſery and confuſion. To prevent all which, and their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitable ruine, I deſire all good men to joyne with me in their prayers to God for an happy and an honourable Union between the King and his Subjects, that <hi>Mercy and Truth may meet together, Righteouſneſſe and Peace kiſſe each other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:47763:5"/>
            <p>Faults eſcaped, correct thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 2. <hi>line</hi> 2. <hi>reade</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 6. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>reade</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> the Presbytery) to ſee it ratified. <hi>p.</hi> 8.<hi> l.</hi> 23. <hi>reade,</hi> this inference.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47763:5"/>
            <head>PALAEMON: OR, THE GRAND RECONCILER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Remember a paſſage in the Preface of a ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Work written by Mr. <hi>H.</hi> one of the Aſſembly, againſt the <hi>Independents:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In that Preface he humbly beſeeches the Honourable Houſes of Parliament to ſettle a Government in the Church, and that with all ſpeed, fearing leſt that if it ſhould continue long without a fence, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Dreſſers and Pruners to purge and weed it, to defend and guard it,<note place="margin">Pſal. 80.13.</note> this <hi>Vineyard.</hi> would bee rooted up by <hi>the wilde Bores out of the wood: Rome</hi> is a wood full of perplexities and errours; The Jeſuited Papiſts are wilde Bores full of cruelty and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice: And beſides theſe, <hi>the little Foxes</hi> (the Schiſmaticks) which we are commanded <hi>to take and kill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 2.15.</note> theſe would devoure the grapes of the Vineyard, and trample all good Orders under their feet, by which meanes there would be laid open a wide gap for all damnable Hereſies, Schiſmes, and Errours, which in a ſhort time would ſpring up and cover the face of the Church. The truth of this we have now found by ſad experience. Two black Devils, <hi>Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Schiſme,</hi> attended with a train of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid opinions raiſed from Hell that region of darkneſſe, have mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in triumph with great boldneſſe in all quarters of our Land, and ſpawned the poyſon of their contagious Tenets, which have beene ſilenced for many ages, and ſcarce heard of till this. And thus whileſt we are diſputing what government is beſt, our Ship is ſinking; and the Church may rightly ſay with ſome alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, what the <hi>Mariners</hi> once to certaine <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> (ſporting
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:47763:6"/>with their danger, and prating <hi>De ente, &amp; non ente</hi> in a ſtorme whilſt they were periſhing) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; Doe you ſport with your pens and tongues whilſt my enemies are diving into my bowels with their ſwords, and raking in my wounds? And well may the Church take up that ſad lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Prophet <hi>Ieremy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>How is the gold become dim, and the moſt fine gold changed, and the ſtones of the Sanctuary are ſcattered in every corner of the ſtreets?</hi> How is the beauty of our Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem defaced? How are the beautifull flowers of this our Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den waſted? I could ſpend many ſheets in ſuch mournfull <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modos:</hi> But as it is the property of a good Phyſitian not to fill his Patients eares with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, but to apply a remedy or a fit cure (and that with care and ſpeed) for his griefe or malady; ſo it is as vaine to weep over a gaſping and dying Church, and not to propoſe a Medicine to prevent its ruine. I dare not be ſo bold as to preſcribe of my ſelfe what Cordiall is fitteſt for a bleeding <hi>State,</hi> and to adviſe how the ruines of this our <hi>Vineyard</hi> may be repaired: Onely this I dare in all humility aſſert, that there are two Fences moſt expedient; the one to keep Gods wrath out, and that is our hearty ſorrow for our ſinnes; the other, good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, to keep good order in, and with it to maintaine qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe and peace within our walls, which peace is Religions Nurſe: My earneſt and hearty deſire of which happy peace (by a bleſſed re-union of the disjoynted members of this Kingdome to their King) moved me to take courage, notwithſtanding the <hi>Tobiahs</hi> and <hi>Sanballats</hi> that oppoſe it, to collect, as was once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, out of the approved Worke of Mr. <hi>Thorndike,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Booke is entituled,</hi> The Primitive Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Churches.</note> a modell of the beſt and moſt ancient Church government, ſetled by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles in the Eaſt and Weſterne Churches, for which we have a full and cleare authority out of the holy Scriptures, and which I doubt not will ſatisfie all parties but the <hi>Independents,</hi> who would turne Chriſtian liberty into licentiouſneſſe, not allowing any Government either in the State or Church.</p>
            <p>The Government which that worthy man labours to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to the judgment of our <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> our State-Governours, is that which is moſt conſiſtent with the Crowne and the Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie of the King, which (as his Majeſty himſelfe confeſſes in his Anſwer to the Nineteen Propoſitions) is tempered and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed with an Ariſtocracie, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Authority of a Parliament
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:47763:6"/>His great Councell to adviſe Him in all affaires which concerne the wel-fare of the State. In reference to which, the Government of the Church founded by the Apoſtles, and which is certainly the onely remedy to prevent diſorders in Eccleſiaſtick and Lay perſons, is a mixt Government, conſiſting of Biſhops and Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters: Which that it was eſtabliſhed by the Apoſtles, he evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences by many enſuing arguments; laying down firſt theſe four undenyable Truths, on which he builds the fabrick of his learned Diſcourſe:
<list>
                  <item>1. That the Apoſtles during the time of their continuance upon earth, took upon them the overſight of thoſe Churches which they planted,</item>
                  <item>2. That each Apoſtle fixed his abode in, and placed his care upon ſome one particular Church, though all the world were to them a Dioceſle; in that they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took to preach the Goſpel to all Nations.</item>
                  <item>3. That the Apoſtles were Biſhops of their ſeverall Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, which they took into their care and charge.</item>
                  <item>4. That the Biſhops were ſucceſſors to the Apoſtles; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were truſted with the overſight of one Church, which the Apoſtles for their owne time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded to all within their Quarters.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I.</head>
               <p>TO illuſtrate the truth of theſe foure Poſitions, and withall to prove that the Churches were at firſt governed by Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Presbyters, he begins with the firſt Church, the Church of Jeruſalem, Mother of all Churches, from whence the ſound of the Goſpel went out into all the world. This Church was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the charge of <hi>Iames,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Alpheus,</hi> one of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and his Presbyters; No doubt by the conſent and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the other Apoſtles, providing for the Church there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their departure into other coa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s.<note place="margin">This is comir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med too by <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius</hi> &amp; <hi>Clem. Alexandrinus.</hi>
                  </note> This appeares by many pregnant paſſages of the Scriptures, as, <hi>Galar</hi> 1.18. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Act.</hi> 15.1, 13, 19. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.12. All theſe places prove that Saint
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47763:7"/>
                  <hi>Iames</hi> had the charge of that Church, as being the chiefe of that firſt Councel held there, of which we reade, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. and<note n="*" place="margin">And when James. Peter and John, &amp;c.</note> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated by S. <hi>Paul</hi> (in that fore-named Epiſtle to the <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.9.) before the reſt of the Apoſtles, ſome of whoſe names wee finde there recorded; To denote his preheminencie and precedencie in that place.</p>
               <p>And that he had Presbyters for his Aſſiſtants, appeares by the ſecond verſe of the fore-cited Chapter of the <hi>Acts. &amp; ch.</hi> 21. <hi>v.</hi> 19. where we find that S. <hi>Paul</hi> at his laſt comming to Jeruſalem,<note place="margin">Acts 15.</note> went in to <hi>Iames,</hi> where all the Elders were preſent, to adviſe with him that had the care of that Church, about the great buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe then in hand, how to behave himſelfe towards thoſe of the Circumciſion who beleeved.</p>
               <p>Of the Colledge of Presbyters at Jeruſalem, and of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence and aſſiſtance with S. <hi>Iames</hi> in the Government of that Church, we have two unreprovable Arguments in the Acts of the Apoſtles, <hi>Act.</hi> 11.30. <hi>Act.</hi> 15.4, 6, 22, 23.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <p>THis pattern thus ſetled in Jeruſalem, the Apoſtles followed in other Churches, which they converted to the Faith by preaching to them the Word of Life. Theſe Churches were firſt founded in Cities, as appears by<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tert. lib. de Praeſcrip. c. 20.</hi> Ac proinde Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſias apud u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nainquam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatem condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derunt.</note> 
                  <hi>Tertullian,</hi> which is moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy our obſervation. For becauſe they could not beſtow their paines equally in all places, reaſon required they ſhould labour moſt to plant the faith of Chriſt in the moſt populous: From whence it was propagated through the Townes and Countryes which were adjacent to thoſe Cities, which therefore in time became and were called the Territories, Pariſhes, or Dioceſes of ſuch or ſuch Churches. Now the form of Government eſtated by S. <hi>Paul</hi> over theſe Churches, is pointed out to us, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.23. where we reade that <hi>Paul and Barnabas ordained them Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in every</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Viz.</hi> in <hi>Lyſtra</hi> and <hi>Derbe,</hi> Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Lyconia, and in <hi>Iconium.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Church. i. e.</hi> Colledges, Bodies or Companies of Presbyters, to order with common advice and joynt conſent the Churches planted by them in ſeverall Cities. This appeares too by the 20. of <hi>Act.</hi> 17. where we find that there was a Bench
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47763:7"/>of Elders at Epheſus, for which <hi>Paul</hi> ſent to <hi>Miletus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Philip 1.</note> Thus in the Church of <hi>Philippi,</hi> you ſhall find that the Apoſtle directed his Epiſtle to the Biſhops and Deacons there, which muſt be to the Colledge of Presbyters next above the Order of Deacons. So when the Apoſtle writeth to the Theſtalonians, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 12. <hi>And we beſeech you brethren to know them which labour among you, and are over you in the Lord:</hi> The multitude whereof he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth is to be underſtood like wiſe of the body or company of the Presbyters. And in all Church Writers you ſhall find continuall remembrance of theſe Presbyters, whenſoever there is ſpeech of Mother Churches in Mother Cities.</p>
               <p>Now the Presbyters being ſtyled in the holy Scriptures by the name of Biſhops, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> a Queſtion will ariſe from hence, Whether the Apoſtles from the beginning ordained Biſhops over the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
               <p>Wee muſt needs anſwer Negatively:<note place="margin">Reſp.</note> And the truth of this will appeare out of <hi>Act.</hi> 20.17. where the Apoſtle uſing theſe words to the Presbyters of Epheſus, <hi>Take heed to your ſelves, and to the whole flocke, over whom the holy Ghoſt hath made you</hi> EPISCOPOS, Biſhops, or Overſeers. Where, as he giveth the name of Biſhops to the Bresbyters, ſo he addreſſeth his inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to none befides. From whence we may probably infer, That at that time there were no Biſhops; If there had been any, S. <hi>Paul</hi> would have mentioned them with reſpect to the eminencie of their office.</p>
               <p>So we finde none at <hi>Philippi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 1.6.</note> as is evident by the Epigraph or Inſcription of that Epiſtle to the Philippians: None in the Church of Corinth, as is collected by S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and others, from the many and great diſorders which the Apoſtle ſharply taxeth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.21. All which happened,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide Tert. de Praeſerip. c</hi> 36. where he calls the fore-named Churches <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoloram Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dras.</hi> By which it appears that the Apoſtles ſate there as chiefe.</note> becauſe there was no Biſhop to compoſe the differences of that Church in the Apoſtles abſence.</p>
               <p>It ſeemes then, that the Apoſtle himſelfe had taken the chiefe charge and overſight of thoſe Churches wherein he had planted bodies of Presbyters. This appears by that place in the 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Beſides thoſe things which are without, that which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth upon me daily, the care of all the Churches.</hi> See <hi>Acts</hi> 15 36. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4. where he proceedeth in the ſentence of Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47763:8"/>againſt the inceſtuous perſon, and requireth of the church (<hi>i.e.</hi> the Presbyter) to ſee it ſatisfied. And the whole frame of his Epiſtles containes the Acts of his Spirituall Government, which he reſerved to himſelf in chiefe over the Churches which he himſelfe had planted. The like may be aſſerted of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> in reſpect of thoſe Churches committed to his charge. <hi>Vid.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1. where he directeth his exhortation of feeding the flocke to none but Presbyters, which St. <hi>Hierome</hi> long ſince has maintained out of the 13. to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> 17. where the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle writeth in the plurall number, <hi>Obey them that have the rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III</head>
               <p>THings being thus ſetled, when the Apoſtles by reaſon of that multitude of buſines, had not leiſure to attend in perſon upon the Churches which they had planted, they appointed certaine Heads or Superintendents over the company of Presbyters, which Heads ever ſince have retained the name of Biſhop.</p>
               <p>Thus were <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> made Biſhops over the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>Crete</hi> and <hi>Aſia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Whoſe Mother Church was <hi>Epheſus.</hi>
                  </note> when it was revealed to the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul,</hi> that from thenceforth he was to make the Weſterne parts of the world his Dioceſſe, <hi>vid. Act.</hi> 19.21. And it was at <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> where S. <hi>Paul</hi> thus beſpake the Elders, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.25. <hi>And now behold, I know that all you among whom I have gone preaching the Kingdome of God ſhall ſee my face no more.</hi> And knowing by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, that hee was to ſerve God no more in thoſe Eaſterne parts,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Tit. 1.5.</note> hee appointed thoſe two Diſciples <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> to be in his ſtead over thoſe Churches: And that their charge was as great as that of Biſhops is not queſtioned by thoſe who are verſed in the moſt ancient Records of our Church. <hi>Quid eſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopus niſi primus Presbyterorum,</hi> ſayes St. <hi>Auguſtine:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> had a full power and authority to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine Presbyters and Deacons, and to fit them with inſtructions to manage their ſeverall offices, we may not doubt out of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ond nicety to ſtile them Biſhops, or Overſcers, for that they were the Heads of their ſeverall Presbyters, and had a <hi>directive</hi> and <hi>coercive</hi> power over them in their particular charges, which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47763:8"/>might be proved by many places in the holy Scriptures. Wee may conclude then that S. <hi>Paul,</hi> in that hee placed two of his prime Diſciples in two principall Cities<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Of</hi> Crete <hi>and</hi> Epheſus.</note> in which there were Presbyters, and gave them in charge to ordaine Presbyters in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very City, as there ſhould be need: Hence (I ſay) we may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre, that our Apoſtle thus ſetling the Eaſterne Churches, and appointing them their Heads and Bodies of Eccleſiaſticall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours,<note place="margin">Rev. 2.3. chap. This is alſo manifeſt by <hi>Ignatius</hi> his Epiſtle, who was S. <hi>Johns</hi> Diſciple, who likewiſe makes often mention of Biſhops and Presbyters.</note> intended to leave a patterne which afterwards ſhould be followed in all Ages. And that this Government was ſetled in <hi>Aſia</hi> under <hi>Timothies</hi> charge, it appeares by S. <hi>Iohns</hi> ſeven Epiſtles ſent from our Lord to the 7. Churches, &amp; directed to the Angels there, who no doubt were Biſhops. And that act of his in directing his Epiſtles to one in the name and behalfe of the whole Church, argues the eminencie of the Head fit to anſwer for the body it repreſenteth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV.</head>
               <p>ANd that the ſame forme of Government which was ſetled in <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> and the forenamed Churches, was likewiſe eſtabliſhed in the Church of <hi>Antioch,</hi> may be proved by that Text in the 13. of <hi>Acts,</hi> where we read,<note place="margin">Act. 12.2.</note> that <hi>there were in the Church of Antiochia certaine Prophets and Teachers, and as they mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred unto the Lord, and faſted, the Holy Ghoſt ſaid, Separate me Barnabas and Saul for the worke whereunto I have called them; and when they had faſted and prayed, and laid their hands upon them, they ſent them away.</hi> It is ſafe to affirme, that theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Teachers were no other then that ranke and order of Presbyters, becauſe we reade, that they miniſtred unto the Lord and gave impoſition of hands, which was the worke of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Miniſters, though that particular impoſition of hands upon <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> was not an ordination of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> but a ſeparation of them, <hi>v.</hi> 2. and deſtinating them to diſtinct Countries. The Heads of the Church were S. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> as appeares by <hi>Ignatius</hi> in his Epiſtle <hi>ad Magn.</hi> where wee have theſe words <hi>For at Antiochia the Diſciples were firſt called Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter founding the Church.</hi> But to untwiſt a doubt which ſome may make, that is, How it came to paſſe, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47763:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>there were two Heads of that Church?<note place="margin">Gal. 2.9, 10.</note> Wee may anſwer, that there were two ſeverall congregations at one and the ſame time there; the one of the Gentiles, called by the Apoſtle Uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion; the other of the Jewes; the care of the one was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to <hi>Peter,</hi> the other to S. <hi>Paul.</hi> Theſe two Apoſtles being called away by their imployments in other parts, tooke the ſame courſe with this Church which before was done by S. <hi>Paul</hi> with thoſe which he commended to the care of <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus:</hi> For, both congregations being by that time united together in a ſweet harmony of Love and Peace, he commended them joyntly to the care of <hi>Euodius</hi> the Biſhop, who was predeceſſour to <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius.</hi> To maintaine yet further the truth of the poſition we are aſſured by the authority of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Corinth,</hi> that <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onyſius</hi> the Areopagite, S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Convert, was Biſhop of <hi>Athens.</hi> In <hi>Alexandria,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 17.34.</note> from <hi>Mark</hi> the Evangeliſt (who was firſt ſet over that Church) there was a continued ſucceſſion of Biſhops and Presbyters, even untill the times of <hi>Heraclas</hi> and <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius,</hi> as Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> witneſſes in his Epiſtle to <hi>Eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grius.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V.</head>
               <p>HAving proved that the Apoſtles ordained Presbyters to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne the Churches planted by their care and paines, the Heads whereof after their departure were Biſhops; from this proofe we may eaſily draw this influence, That the government of the Churches was for a long time upheld in common by Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Presbyters, as from the beginning the Presbyters go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned joyntly with the Apoſtles. This inference Mr. <hi>Th.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes at large by many demonſtrative and undenyable argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>viz.</hi> p. 69, 70, 71. where out of <hi>Ignatius</hi> his Epiſtle <hi>ad Tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ianos,</hi> and the Commentaries under S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his name upon 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.1. he proves what has been aſſerted.<note place="margin">Nothing was done in the Churchly the Biſhop without his Presbyters advice and conſent.</note> S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his words are theſe, <hi>Apud omnes utique gentes honorabilis eſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nectus, unde &amp; Synagoga &amp; poſtea Eccleſia ſeniores habuit ſine quorum conſilio nihil agebatur in Eccleſiâ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This likewiſe is confirmed by S. <hi>Hierome</hi> upon <hi>Titus</hi> 1.5. and by the Authority of S. <hi>Cyprian, Ep.</hi> 6. And by reaſon of this
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47763:9"/>concurrence of the Presbyters with the Biſhops in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, it is, that the moſt ancient Church Writers comprized both Biſhops and Prebyters under the ſame titles, entitling the Biſhops Presbyters, not becauſe there were then no Biſhops (as ſome fondly deeme) but becauſe both concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (as hath been ſaid) in a joynt care of managing the affaires of the Church.</p>
               <p>That their names were confounded Mr. <hi>Th.</hi> proves out of the Epiſtle of <hi>Clemens, vide</hi> p. 54. and out of <hi>Ignatius</hi> his Epiſtle to <hi>Hero</hi> his Deacon;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vi. Euſeb. Ecc. Hiſt. p.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 23. where one and the ſame is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and alſo out of <hi>Tertul. de praeſcrip.</hi> c. 3. The Apoſtle S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſtiles himſelf an Elder, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. of which no other reaſon can be given but this, that he ſo termes himſelf both in regard of his age, &amp; in regard of his office, which was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in the care of the Church with the Presbyters. To evince farther that there was ever a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munity of names, though a diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the order and office of Biſhops and Presbyters, he cites a place out of <hi>Tertull:</hi> in his <hi>Apol.</hi> c. 39. <hi>Praeſident probati quic<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſeniores, &amp;c.</hi> where by the name of Elders or Presbyters, is to be underſtood the order of Biſhops; With this of <hi>Tertullian</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords that of S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> in his 1. Book <hi>de Offic. vid. c.</hi> 20. and of <hi>Irenaeus, l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 43. both which authorities you may reade at large in Mr. <hi>Th.</hi> book, <hi>p.</hi> 77, 78, 79. And that both rankes or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Biſhops and Presbyters were comprized under the name of <hi>Praepoſiti</hi> and <hi>Praeſidentes,</hi> is cleare, as appeares by that place of <hi>Tertull. de Cor. Mil. c.</hi> 3. <hi>Euchariſtiae Sacramentum nec de aliorum manu quam Praeſidentium ſumimus.</hi> The like we finde in S. <hi>Cyprian, Ep.</hi> 62. By all which it is manifeſt, that both or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders had common Names in regard of the community of their office and charge.</p>
               <p>As for the forme it ſelfe, of this Church-conſiſtory, the mixt Government of Biſhops and Presbyters, it relates to a patterne in the Synagogue of the Jewes, for it reſembles their publike Court of Juſtice, which they called the Sanedrin, a great part whereof were Prieſts and Levites, and had the hearing of all ſorts of cauſes. We have S. <hi>Ierome</hi> for our Advocate to confirme this reſemblance between the Biſhops and Presbyters, and that high Court of the Jewes.</p>
               <p>He in his Comment upon <hi>Titus,</hi> ſpeaking of Biſhops con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47763:10"/>with Presbyters, ſayes thus, <hi>Imitantur Moyſen qui cum haberet in poteſtate ſua praeeſſe populo Iſraeletico ſeptunginta elegit cum quibus populum judicavit.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vid. R. Moſes in Halacoth Sanedrin. c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> But when <hi>Moſes</hi> was dead, a Preſident was choſen over and above the ſeventy whom they called the <hi>Naſi,</hi> who from age to age ſupplyed <hi>Moſes</hi> place, and ſuch as the <hi>Naſi</hi> was over the Seventy, is a Biſhop over the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, <hi>i. e.</hi> chiefe both in Dignity and Office; of which there are two parts, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to rule the Church, (<hi>i. e.</hi> to keep thoſe that be under him in obedience to good Lawes) and to performe divine ſervice, to Pray and Preach, and to adminiſter the Sacraments.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VI.</head>
               <p>NOw becauſe there be ſome who draw this compariſon into conſequence, labouring to prove that the Presbyteries ought to conſiſt part of Elders of the people, and part of Church Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, as the Sanedrin was made up of Prieſts, Levites, and Laikes. They muſt know that the Sanedrin conſiſted of the chiefe of the People, as well as Prieſts and Levites, becauſe the chiefe cauſes of the Commonwealth as well as of Religion, paſſed through their hands, and were referred to their judgements. The Church in all temporall matters is ſubject to the Lawes and authority of the Commonwealth: But in thoſe things which concerne the Soule, can we imagine that our Lord did leave her to the charge of any but to thoſe who are truſted with the Keyes of his Houſe, who are ſpirituall men, ſet apart and appointed for the cure of ſoules? But to prove that the Presbyteries then in uſe conſiſted of none but Miniſters of the Church, it will not be amiſſe, firſt to cleare that Text in <hi>Timothie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.17.</note> which they urge who labour to maintaine that Lay perſons were in the Apoſtles times admitted into Presbyteries. <hi>Let the Elders that rule well be counted worthy of double honour, eſpecially thoſe that labour in the Word and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</hi> Theſe words carry at the firſt ſound an appearance of two ſorts of Elders, the one of which they would have <hi>Preachers,</hi> the other onely <hi>Rulers.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.2.</note> But we muſt anſwer this Objection, firſt by an undeniable aſſertion taken out of St. <hi>Peters</hi> exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47763:10"/>to his Presbyters, and out of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> charge to the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters of Epheſus, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.<note place="margin">Act. 20.28.</note> Both their exhortations imply thus much, That the Presbyters duty did conſiſt in this, to <hi>feed</hi> the Flocke of Chriſt, and to <hi>overſee</hi> it. We aſſert therefore that their office was both to <hi>govern</hi> and to <hi>teach;</hi> both which are plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intimated in thoſe qualities which the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2, 5. aſcribes as proper to Biſhops, <hi>i. e.</hi> (as Mr. <hi>Th.</hi> acknowledges) to Presbyters. Both too are contained in that very paſſage which is alledged to evince the neceſſity of Lay-Elders; for thoſe <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that rule well</hi> are ſuch <hi>as labour in the Word and Doctrine.</hi> Secondly, to the objection we anſwer thus, That in that place the Apoſtle intended only to difference the Presbyters by the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of their functions, and not to make any difference in the functions themſelves:<note place="margin">Reade Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition upon that Text of 1 Tim. 5.17. <hi>Vid. Medes Diatr.</hi>
                  </note> For the function and office was one and the ſame, belonging to one and the ſame Eccleſiaſtique perſon, his office was to <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>teach;</hi> this latter was rightly accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the moſt eminent point of that Function; he that took ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall paines in this, (which the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> implyes) and withall did rule well, was worthy of double honour in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and this in the judgement of the moſt learned Interpreters is conceived to be the meaning of the Text.</p>
               <p>Againe, what if we ſhould not deny,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.4. &amp;c. Rom. 12.6. 1 Cor. 12.28.</note> but confeſſe what is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and cleare by many Texts, that the Holy Ghoſt diſtributed in that infancy of the Church many perſonall gifts and ſpeciall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments on ſeverall perſons to be employed in the edification of particular Aſſemblies; amongſt which gifts this of <hi>ruling</hi> might be one, which the Holy Ghoſt might beſtow on ſome to aſſiſt the Presbyters in their government. Although this be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to have been in the time of the Apoſtles, yet if any man ſhould now preſume to draw their example into imitation, I would ask him this queſtion; What commiſſion he or any man has to turne temporary indowments into perpetuall places? I am ſure he has none. What might be expedient in the Apoſtles dayes, may not be thought convenient in ours. And if we ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to doe now what then was done, I feare the world would be turned upſide downe, and all things brought to confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. But to conclude this grand Controverſie betweene <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Geneva;</hi> Mr. <hi>Th.</hi> who comes not ſhort of any in the skill of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47763:11"/>Antiquity, aſſures us that we ſhall never finde in any ancient Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor the leaſt mention of Lay-Elders in the government of the Church in that manner as is practiſed by the Geneviſts. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary he proves out of <hi>Tertullian,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 106.108.</note> and out of the Commentaries under St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his name upon <hi>Titus:</hi> by which it is manifeſt that the Elders then in uſe were <hi>Doctores,</hi> ſuch as were employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Miniſtery of the Word and Sacraments.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VII.</head>
               <p>THis great doubt being, I ſuppoſe, cleared, and it being ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently proved, that Lay-Elders have no right to the ordering of Church affaires, or medling with ſpirituall things which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the good and welfare of mens ſoules: Mr. <hi>Th.</hi> proceeds to diſcover out of the moſt ancient Authors what were the bounds of the office of Biſhop and Presbyter, and in what caſes the Biſhop had the preeminence.</p>
               <p>He tells us that the office of Divine Service, <hi>i. e.</hi> of Teaching or Preaching and adminiſtring the Sacraments, were wont to be reſerved to the Biſhop in honour of his place and eminency of it.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>i. e.</hi> when he came into any Church the Presbyter ever gave way to him to preach.</note> This is witneſſed by <hi>Juſt. Martyr,</hi> who relates in plaine termes that the Sermon uſed to be made, and the Euchariſt celebrated by the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or Biſhop; ſo that the Presbyters did not preach but when the Biſhop was abſent, and adminiſtred not the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>i. e.</hi> did not conſecrate in his preſence. This is evident in the life of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> by the ſtory of <hi>Valerius,</hi> a Greek Biſhop, who comming into St. <hi>Auſtines</hi> Church at <hi>Hippo,</hi> deſired Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> (who was not then a Biſhop) to officiate, in regard that he was not well skilled in the African, nor the people in the knowledge of the Greek tongue. <hi>Tertullian</hi> affirmes the ſame, <hi>l. de Bapt. c.</hi> 17. ſo does <hi>Ignatius in Epiſt. ad Smyrn.</hi> Where to ſhew the preeminence of the Biſhop he proves, that as by the ancient conſtitutions of the Church the Presbyters ought not to doe any thing without the conſent of the Biſhop, nor the Biſhop in great matters without the conſent and advice of his Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſo neither ought the Laity to doe any thing in the Church without the Biſhop and Presbyters approbation or liking.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47763:11"/>This may be farther proved out of <hi>Ignatius</hi> in his <hi>Epiſt. ad Trall.</hi> And ſo ſtill in <hi>Ignatius</hi> the Presbyters are aſſiſtant to the Biſhop in all things. Which is likewiſe confirmed by the ſixth Canon of the Councell of <hi>Gangra. Vi.</hi> Mr. <hi>Th. p.</hi> 118, 119. Where hee alſo proves that the Deacons were not <hi>ſuijuris, i. e.</hi> had not the ſole diſpoſing of the maintenance of the Church and poore, but did onely execute the will and judgement of the Biſhop and Presbyters, and diſtributed the Churches almes to thoſe whom they appointed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VIII.</head>
               <p>HAving thus declared in part the preeminence of the Biſhop over the Presbyters, <hi>i. e.</hi> the priviledge he has in ſome caſes above theſe, and alſo that the Deacons as well as the Lay-perſons are ſubject to the power of both the former, Mr. <hi>Th.</hi> proceeds to diſcourſe of two particulars in the Office common to Biſhops and Presbyters, wherein the people have a ſhare, and may claim an intereſſe.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>The one is the diſcipline of Penance;</item>
                  <item>The other the ordaining of Miniſters.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And firſt of all by way of manuduction to his diſcourſe, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines that Text, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.19. <hi>And I will give thee the keyes of heaven: And whatſoever thou bindeſt on earth ſhall be bound in heaven; whatſoever thou ſhalt looſe on earth, ſhall be looſed in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> Which power of binding and looſing he affirmes to be the ſame with that given to the Apoſtles, <hi>John</hi> 20.24. <hi>Whoſoever ſins ye remit they are remitted unto him: and whoſe ſoever ſins ye retain they are retained.</hi> The Biſhop and Presbyters that exerciſed this power of binding and looſing, remitting and retaining ſins, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented the office of <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Phyſitians:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lapſis fratri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus per poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam mede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la quaeratur. <hi>Firmil. in Ep. ad Cypr. Ep. 75.</hi>
                  </note> Judges they were in ſhutting Gods houſe upon offenders, and binding their ſinnes upon their conſciences; Phyſitians, in preſcribing the medicine of repentance: And in that reſpect alone are ſaid to remit ſinnes; (as a Phyſitian who does no more but preſcribe the medicine, or at the moſt ſee it preſcribed, is ſaid to cure a mans diſeaſe.) And having a ſpirituall eye to judge when repentance is ſound and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained, upon due knowledge of this they may aſſure men that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:47763:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>their ſinnes are pardoned, and pronounce their abſolution decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively, whereby they unlooſe that knot wherewith their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences were tyed.</p>
               <p>The medicine of Repentance preſcribed to a delinquent, was wont to be ſtrengthened with the prayers and interceſſion of the Congregation, but in the chiefe place of the Biſhop and Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, whoſe prayers were correſpondent to that which is given to make phyſick work. <hi>Vi. Mat.</hi> 18.19. out of which text follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that wherein Chriſt gives to the Apoſtles power of binding and looſing, may be proved that the Congregation interceding by their prayers with God for a ſinner, in this reſpect bore a part, and had a ſhare with the Church, (the Biſhop and Presbyters) in the diſcipline of penance which theſe impoſed upon delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents; but<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>i. e.</hi> The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation or people.</note> they medled not with the keyes of Gods houſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> they did not (as the Jewes were wont to doe) uſurpe the power of Excommunication upon cauſes of their particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſe, but left that wholly to the Church, <hi>i. e.</hi> to the Ecceleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Governours, to whom only that power did belong. <hi>Dic Eccleſiae, Matth.</hi> 18.17. implyes as much. That cenſure of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication (as appeares by 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.13.) did cut men off from the converſation of Chriſtians, (for that ſuch perſons for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited by their hainous ſinnes the priviledge of Gods ſonnes) and ſo delivered them over to the power of Satan, to be led captive by him at his will and pleaſure: As thoſe among the Iſraelites that lodged without the Camp were in danger to be lickt up and devoured by the Amalekites. That courſe of Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as it was a preſervative in regard of thoſe that were not tain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, yet might be, ſo was it medicinall in reſpect of the ſicke which were uſually reſtored to their former ſoundneſſe by ſhame and griefe:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vi.</hi> 1 Cor. 5.6 1 Tim. 1.20.</note> and this power of excommunicating was exerciſed in common by the Biſhops and Presbyters: which practice was a good gloſſe upon the words of our Saviour to <hi>Peter, Behold, I give thee the keyes of heaven:</hi> for what was promiſed to <hi>Peter</hi> was given to his fellow Apoſtles, but was to reſt in the Church throughout all ages. Witneſſe that of Saint <hi>Auſtine, Ep.</hi> 79. <hi>Si hoc in Eccleſiâ fit, Petrus quando claves accepit Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiam ſanctam ſignificavit. Vid.</hi> Mr. <hi>Th. p.</hi> 143. where you ſhall finde for the confirmation of this an authority out of <hi>Tertull.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:47763:12"/>Apol. c.</hi> 39. and another out of St. <hi>Auſt. Homil. ult. ex</hi> 50. <hi>Hom. c.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>How becauſe the Church cannot proceed in their Cenſures effectually or to any good purpoſe, but by vertue of thoſe lawes which are put in force and maintained by the Secular powers; and becauſe it cannot be expected that the people ſhould yeeld a voluntary ſubmiſſion to the Diſcipline of the Church, farther then it is enabled by the Lawes of the Realme to exerciſe it; Therefore it is much to be wiſhed that thoſe wholeſome and uſefull Lawes, by which the Miniſters of the Church are enabled, directed, and conſtrained to exerciſe and diſcharge this neceſſary part of their office, may be revived and put into act; that ſo the power of the Keyes given to the Church by our Lord, being aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted and ſtrengthned by the Secular arme, may be enabled to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce all notorious offenders to a good life and converſation by the Diſcipline of penance, and to cut them off from the Church that refuſe it. Then this Diſcipline of penance there is not a more puiſſant way to beat down Vice, and to diſcountenance Malefactors in a Chriſtian Commonwealth: In regard that when they have ſatisfied the Lawes of the Kingdome with the loſſe of goods and reputation, or have eſcaped death by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivence and gentleneſſe of their Judges. Nevertheleſſe if the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline of the Church were exerciſed upon them, they ſhould not communicate with the people of God, till the Church were ſatisfied of their correction and amendment. This alſo would give ſatisfaction to the tender conſciences of thoſe good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, who like to thoſe in St. <hi>Cpyrians</hi> time are ſcandalized when they ſee them admitted to the Communion who live (without any the leaſt amendment) in a conſtant practice and profeſſion of ſinne. There being then ſo much good,<note place="margin">Cypr. Ep. <hi>551.</hi>
                  </note> and the prevention of ſo much ill contained in the Diſcipline of penance, let it be the hearty deſire of all knowing and well-affected Chriſtians to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the State and Church, that the Diſcipline commended to us by our Saviour, and practiſed by the Apoſtles, may be with all care and ſpeed reformed and brought againe into uſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:47763:13"/>
               <head>SECT. IX.</head>
               <p>HAving thus unfolded the nature of that power wherewith Chriſt inveſted his Apoſtles, and from them derived it to his Church, and that is the power of the Keyes, whereof there be two appendixes, Excommunication and the Diſcipline of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, Mr. <hi>Th.</hi> proceeds to the diſcovery of the other part of the Churches Office, and that is the conſtituting and ordaining of Miniſters, of which there be ſome <hi>veſtigia</hi> or footſteps left for our imitation in the holy Scriptures, as, when they had faſted and prayed, and laid their hands on them, they ſent them away, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.3. <hi>Act.</hi> 14.23. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Neglect not the gift that was given thee by Prophecie, with the impoſition of the hands of the Presbyterie:</hi> which words are expounded, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. <hi>by impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my hands;</hi> ſo likewiſe 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. To which we may adde the choice of <hi>Matthias, Act.</hi> 1.23. and that paſſage in the choice of the ſeven Deacons, <hi>Act.</hi> 6.3. <hi>Looke ye out among you ſeven men of honeſt report:</hi> and <hi>verſe</hi> 5. and 6. <hi>They choſe Steven and the reſt, and ſet them before the Apoſtles, and when they had prayed they laid their hands upon them.</hi> Which place is alledged by St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> to prove that the people have an intereſſe, and ought to have a ſhare in the ordination of Miniſters. And that this was the cuſtome and practice of the Primitive Church to publiſh the names of thoſe perſons who were to be ordained, that ſo the people diſcuſſing their lives and manners, might by their approbation ratifie the ordination of ſuch whom they knew to be men well gifted, and of an holy converſation. This ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by a remarkable paſſage in the life of <hi>Alexander Severus,</hi> by an excellent ſaying of St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> to this purpoſe,<note place="margin">Ordinationes Sacerdotum ſub populi aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtentis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientia fieci. <hi>Cypr.</hi>
                  </note> and by the 6. Canon of the Councell of <hi>Chalcedon.</hi> By all which it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that the people did not nominate, but onely approve by their common ſuffrage and conſent the perſons who were to be ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. And that the Biſhop did adviſe with his Presbyters about the nomination of thoſe who were to be ordained Deacons or Miniſters, this is cleare by thoſe words of St. <hi>Cyprian, Ep.</hi> 54. where he excuſeth himſelfe to his Clergy, that he had ordained
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:47763:13"/>
                  <hi>Saturus</hi> and <hi>Optatus</hi> alone, without their conſent and approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. By this we may collect what was practiſed in that age of the Church.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Firſt, there was a nomination or publication of the perſons names to the people.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, upon their knowledge and approbation of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to be ordained, there followed impoſition of hands, wherein conſiſted the accompliſhment of the whole work, which is therefore called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in Greek.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Concerning the Ordination of Biſhops onely this may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verred out of Saint <hi>Hierome,</hi> who hath recorded that in the Church of <hi>Alexandria</hi> the Presbyters were wont to chooſe a Biſhop out of their owne Claſſis or rank: yet we muſt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that the firſt conſtitution of a Biſhop there, who was <hi>Hana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> was made by <hi>Marke</hi> the Euangeliſt, as we may ſee in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichius,</hi> lately ſet forth by Mr. <hi>Selden.</hi> And it is evident out of many other Authors, that they nominated the perſon to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of by the people, and to be ordained by the neighbour Biſhops. This too is maintained by Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. upon <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.2. Where wee muſt underſtand by thoſe words, <hi>Multorum Sacerdotum judicium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Non ordo ſed meritum crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat Epiſcopum multorum Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotum judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio conſtitutum &amp;c. Vi. Can. <hi>19.</hi> Concil. Antioc.</note> as well the judgement of the Presbyters by whom the Biſhop was elected, as of the Biſhops of other Churches by whom he was ordained, and with whom he was to preſerve the unity of the Church. And unleſſe three Biſhops at the leaſt were preſent, it was not uſuall to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine one. Thus without conſent of the Biſhops all procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of the Clergy and people were quite diſabled, and to no purpoſe in the Primitive times.</p>
               <p>And although the Biſhops in ſome Churches uſurped the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Ordination of Miniſters without the conſent of their Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters,<note place="margin">Vi. Chryſ. Hom. <hi>2.</hi> in <hi>1</hi> Tim. It. Hieron. in Ep. ad Euagr.</note> however it is manifeſt by the joynt conſent of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (who witneſſe that the Presbytery was a Bench aſſiſtant to the Biſhop, without advice whereof nothing of moment was done or acted) &amp; by the practice of the Apoſtles, that the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ought to have a ſhare with the Biſhop in the impoſition of hands.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.14. 2 Tim. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Timothy</hi> received impoſition of hands from Saint <hi>Paul</hi> and the Presbyters of <hi>Autiochia.</hi> This laſt Theſis may be confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the authority of Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> who oft expreſſes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in this particular, That he would never ordaine any with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the advice of his Presbyters, and conſent of the people:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:47763:14"/>which advice implyes that they concurred with him in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of Miniſters. And as for impoſition of hands, that the Presbyters alſo conjoyned with the Biſhops in this, it is evident by the 22.<note place="margin">Epiſcopus ſine Concilio Cleri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum ſuorum Clericos non ordinet; ita ut civium aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum &amp; teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monium quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat.</note> Canon of the fourth Councell of <hi>Carthage,</hi> and by the aforeſaid Epiſtle of <hi>Firmilianus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ceſarea Cappadocia:</hi> as alſo by <hi>Ignatius</hi> his Epiſtle to <hi>Hero.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By all theſe authorities it evidently appeares that the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters concurred with the Biſhops in the act of Ordination, aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting them by their prayers, gracing them by their preſence, and countenancing their act by a joint conſent in their Suffrages.</p>
               <p>The like is affirmed in the fourth Councell of Carthage, <hi>c.</hi> 3. where it is provided and appointed, that when the Biſhop giveth impoſition of hands, the Presbyters alſo ſhall impoſe theirs by his, which they did to argue their conſent to what was done by the Biſhop.<note place="margin">In which act the people had no ſhare.</note> And this joynt act of the Biſhop and Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters in laying their hands upon the heads of the Miniſters, ſignified the overſhadowing of the Holy Ghoſt, which they then prayed might light upon them who are to be ordained.</p>
               <p>As for the conſtituting and ordaining of Biſhops, the advice of Mr. <hi>Th.</hi> is moſt obſervable and waighty. He adviſes in the firſt place, that with all circumſpection and providence great care be uſed <hi>in ordering the choice of them.</hi> His meaning is that if the people in the primitive Church had an intereſſe or ſhare in giving conſent to thoſe who were to be ordained Presbyters, much more muſt we think it very juſt and fit, that the votes of the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and conſent of the people ſhould now precede and concur in the deſigning of ſuch perſons, under whom and with whom they are to guide and be guided in ſpirituall affaires; ſuch perſons are Biſhops who ſhould be men moſt holy in their life, and moſt eminent for learning. Moſt happy would this Nation be if all our Prelates were ſuch; and if that preſcribed method were duly obſerved in the choice, ſuch would there alwayes or for the moſt part be, who ſhould fit at the Helme of this poore diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Church, now like to that Ship in which <hi>Peter</hi> was toſſed, and ready to ſink for want of good Pilots.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>SECT. X.</head>
               <p>LAſt of all, becauſe this Apoſtolicall government by Biſhops and Presbyters is chiefly exerciſed in Ordination &amp; Penance, a queſtion may ariſe, Whether it belongs to the Biſhop alone,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:47763:14"/>without his Presbyters, to cenſure the offences (whether in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine or manners) of thoſe perſons who have received holy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. Mr. <hi>Th.</hi> clearing firſt that place in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.19, 20. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers the queſtion,<note place="margin">Againſt an El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der receive not an accuſation but under 2. or 3. witneſſes, &amp;c.</note> That without all doubt it was the practice of the primitive times for the Biſhop with his Presbyters to take the examination of offending Miniſters, whom, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed of their offence by the mouth, (<hi>i. e.</hi> the aſſeveration) of 2. or 3. witneſſes, he in the preſence of his Presbyters did rebuke before all in the ſight and hearing of the congregation, that others thereby might be ſtrucken with feare to offend God and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by their ſcandalous converſation. If this courſe had been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken formerly with Miniſters and Deacons, it might have ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God that the Church ſhould not now have layen bleeding and gaſping in this fatall ruine: Neither would there have beene gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to our enemies ſo juſt an occaſion of relating ſad truths in <hi>Gath</hi> and <hi>Askelon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus following the method of that moſt learned Gentleman, I have caſt his larger Modell into a leſſer frame, that the cmmon people may hereby be better inſtructed and adviſed not to thinke of deſtroying Biſhops, but rather labour and wiſh for the reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of their Presbyteries; which forme of government being ſet downe and delivered in the holy Scriptures, is commended and countenanced by the agreement of hiſtoricall Truth, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive practice, as of the Apoſtles and other ſucceeding ages. And ſeeing that the Biſhops ſucceeded the Apoſtles in <hi>place</hi> and <hi>function,</hi> I cannot but wonder that thoſe ſhould endeavour to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them, thoſe who are Sons of the Apoſtles Faith and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. S. <hi>Hierom</hi> of all Church Writers leaſt favorable to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Biſhops, is nevertheleſſe moſt large in acknowledging that without it the peace of particular Churches could not be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. In witneſſe whereof we may appeale to thoſe many and happy dayes which our Church ſince the Reformation by means of it hath enjoyed, without ſuch ruptures and factions which have happened in a neighbouring Church, whoſe people were alwayes obſerved to be of all others moſt daring, in matters of Religion, to innovate opinions, and break the bonds of peace, by which the good and welfare of Church and State is promoted. To re-eſtabliſh which bleſſed peace (after which we groane in our prayers with panting deſires) it could be wiſhed that wee might ſee the Heads of our Church, the Biſhops, <hi>ſtand</hi> (as Mr.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:47763:15"/>
                  <hi>Th.</hi> expreſſes it well) <hi>in their right places,</hi> being ſet over Bodies or Colledges of Presbyteries, which ſhould conſiſt of men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to the Church both in Doctrine and Diſcipline. To the want of which government, although ſome have attributed thoſe many inconvenciences wherewith the Church is cumbred, yet moſt of the Clergy-men that are verſed in the affaires of the Church, wiſhing its proſperity and peace, doe acknowledge and confeſſe with a proteſtation againſt it, That there is one in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency now ſetled in the Church, which has done much miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, and cannot be redreſſed without a publique Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: It is the committing of <hi>Juriſdiction at large</hi> (even that which by the power of the Keyes received from Chriſt is proper and eſſentiall to the Church) to Lay perſons, as Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors and Commiſſaries &amp;c. who may ſtill retaine that office and ranke they hold in regard of thoſe other points of Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in charitable cauſes annexed by the favour of Princes and Lawes of Commonwealths to the Church,<note place="margin">As the probat of Wils, &amp;c.</note> which is fitteſt to judge and determine in ſuch caſes, yet may be nonpluſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for want of knowledge in the Civill Law, and therefore may and muſt have need of ſuch aſſiſtants; who, if they moved onely in the lower Sphere of the Law, and medled not with that <hi>Primum mobile,</hi> the great wheele of the Church, the diſcipline of penance, but did leave the execution of this to the Biſhop and Presbyters. If this were once amended, and officers duly cenſured by the B<hi rend="sup">ps</hi> &amp; their Presbyters openly in the Church, or in any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like place of Juſtice: And beſides the exerciſe of this diſcipline, if they enjoined their joint pains &amp; parts in the tryall &amp; examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of perſons who come for Ordination, providing that none be ordained but thoſe who are either Aſſiſtants of, and are preſented to Cures (according to our Lawes) if this were faithfully done, and Miniſters without connivence cenſured who ſhould offend either in life or doctrine, then ſhould we ſee Righteouſneſſe run downe like a ſtreame in our ſtreets, and Peace would flouriſh within our wals, and Plenty in our palaces.</p>
               <p>This is my daily prayer, and it is the deſire of all good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians:
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Da pacem Domine in diebus noſtris.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Give peace in our time O Lord.</l>
                     <l>O pray for the peace of Jeruſalem.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:47763:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47763:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Kinde Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The Authors of this Book being by multiplicity of imployments detained from meeting together to reviſe the whole before the impreſſion was fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, the <hi>Errata</hi> ſwell to a greater number then may ſtand with the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of the Book, but if thou pleaſeſt before the reading of it, with thy pen to correct theſe enſuing, we hope it will tend the more to thy ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>PAge 1. line 5. 1 Joh. 5.22. read Joh. 5.22. p. 5. l. 26. <hi>blot out</hi> [is]. p. 6. l. 22. <hi>in ſome Copies</hi> [comparing] r. conforming. p. 52. l. 19. three, r. two. and l. 20. <hi>blot out theſe words</hi> [3. It is an exerciſed power] p. 73. l. 6. <hi>in margin</hi> [potentiſſima] r. potiſſima. p. 75. l. 7. ſerve r. ſwear. p. 82. l. 3. conventies. r. conventions. and l. 34. eſſentiall r. ſeverall. p. 84. l. 14. ſubject, r. direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and properly ſubordinate. p. 85. l. 33. eſſentiall r. ſeverall. p. 87. l 4. ſeeing, r. preaching. p. 95. l. 36, 37. <hi>blot out thoſe words</hi> [God hath not given us the ſpirit of feare but of power, Tit. 1.7.] p. 96. l. 25. 1 Cor. 19. r. 1 Cor. 14. p. 103. l. 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> p. 111. l. 1. to 5. <hi>blot out the ſentence from</hi> [ſuppoſing] <hi>to the period.</hi> and l. 10. perfect, r. profeſt. p. 111. l. 7. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in no. r. but a. p. 115. l. 5. <hi>blot out</hi> [joyntly]. p. 118. l. 3. <hi>blot out theſe words</hi> [3. He that ſheweth mercy, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſuch as were to entertain ſtrangers, relieve the ſick, &amp;c. ver. 8.] p. 121. l. 10. <hi>blot out</hi> [yet] p. 123. l. 34. <hi>blot out</hi> [well] p. 169. l. 11. 1 Cor. 4.21. r. 1 Cor. 4.20. p. 172. l. 17. <hi>blot out</hi> [of the Church] p. 195. l. 5. a multitude r. multitudes. p. 214. l. 28. <hi>blot out</hi> [greater], and l. 29. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Other literall faults will be pardoned of courſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:47763:16"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
